Well, now it's time to talk about what
was happening on the home front during
World War I. And unless you're a fan of
government suppression of civil
liberties, then I'd say that the
developments on the home front left a
little to be desired. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Now, probably the
biggest change on the home front during
World War I was the expansion of the
federal government in the lives of
Americans, which in many ways was a
continuity from the progressive era. And
if you want to know why, and I know that
you do, then let me explain it up real
nice for you. So, as you may or may not
know, World War I is an example of what
we'd call a total war, which by
definition is a war that requires a
state to leverage all of its resources,
both at home and abroad, in order to
fight. And so, in the process of waging
a total war, significant sacrifices were
required of Americans on the home front.
And that created an environment in which
the federal government gained more
control over American society. For
example, President Woodrow Wilson
applied his passion for progressivist
efficiency to the creation of government
agencies that organized the American
economy and society around war
production. And I'll just give you a
couple of examples. So the War
Industries Board worked with private
sector corporations to help them prepare
to ramp up production to manufacture war
supplies. And the National War Labor
Board represented labor unions and
corporations and worked to make sure
that businesses treated their workers
fairly while also ensuring that unions
would not organize strikes and slow down
war production. And I could go on, but
the point is in order to successfully
fight in World War I, the federal
government became heavily involved in
the country's economic affairs. And the
upside to that is that it created lots
of jobs and really got the economy
cranking. But as you may have guessed,
there was also a downside to the
government takeover of American society.
And I shall bum you out about it
presently. Oh, and by the way, if you
want note guys to follow along with this
video and all my videos, check the link
in the description. So yeah, for all the
upsides of government intervention in
the war years, the downsides were real
nasty. And the nastiest of all was the
restriction of American civil liberties.
And there are three categories here
you're going to need to know. First, the
government restricted Americans freedom
of speech. You see, because conducting a
war at this scale was an intense and
delicate process, the government
considered widespread descent as an
existential threat to victory. And so,
the federal government went ahead and
ordered a tall glass of shut the heck up
to any American who decided they wanted
to criticize the war effort. For
example, in 1917, Congress passed the
Espionage Act, which made participating
in anti-war activities illegal, most
notably interfering with the military
draft. And then in 1918, the Sedition
Act prohibited Americans from expressing
anti-government beliefs or displaying
any kind of disloyalty to their
government. And I know that sounds kind
of scary, but don't worry because if
anyone broke those laws, then they were
arrested and went to actual jail. For
example, in 1918, the Socialist Party
leader Eugene V. Debs was arrested after
a speech in which he compared the
military draft to slavery. And for thus
speaking his mind, Deb spent 10 years in
prison. Like 10 years for flapping his
mouth hole. Insane. But I'm sure the
Supreme Court's going to come in and
save the day and keep the government
from trampling on Americans
constitutionally protected right to
speech. But here's where I tell you not
so much. Yeah. In a case called Shank v.
the United States, the court ruled that
it is indeed permissible to restrict
free speech if that speech presents a
clear and present danger to national
security. And so taken altogether, these
developments severely restricted
Americans right to free speech. And that
signaled a shift that the federal
government's wartime policies
prioritized national security above
first amendment protections. And then
the second example of restrictions of
civil liberties during the war is a
series of attacks on immigrant culture.
So, not surprisingly, German Americans
were viewed with suspicion since they
were related by heritage to the hated
enemy of the war. And so, in 1917, a
group of nivists with sponsorship from
the Department of Justice formed the
American Protective League. And its
members were tasked with spying on their
German-American neighbors and reporting
any disloyal behavior that they
observed. And although their methods
often bordered on illegal, the group
turned up little to no evidence of
German spies in the American population.
And finally, the third example of
restrictions on civil liberties was the
Red Scare. And this whole panic started
because in 1917, Russians decided to go
ahead and have their Russian revolution
and transform themselves into a
communist state. And apparently there
was no faster way to cause American
policymakers to poop their pants than to
hear about communism at such a massive
scale entering the world stage. But then
even more alarming was the founding of
the common turn, which was a group of
Russian leaders whose stated goal was to
start communist revolutions in
capitalist countries throughout the
world. So combine both of those
developments with the growing unlabor
arrest and strikes in the post-war
period and it created the fuel for
further government repression of
American civil liberties. And since the
espionage and sedition acts were still
in force, the federal government made
use of those lingering wartime powers to
squash descent after the war. And so the
most visible representation of the Red
Scare came in the Palmer raids of 1919
and 1920 which was spearheaded by US
Attorney General Mitchell Palmer after a
suspected radical bombed his house which
was only one in a series of similar
bombings. Now, Palmer along with
President Wilson happened to believe
that America's greatest threat came in
the form of radical immigrants from
Russia and other southern and eastern
European nations. And by the hammer of
Thor, they intended to find them and get
them out. And so, the Palmer raids began
and resulted in federal agents arresting
more than 6,000 immigrants with little
to no legal justification. They were
often jailed without being told why. And
in the end, several hundred immigrants
were deported. And as you can imagine,
this whole scenario sent fear into
American immigrant communities because
the message from the government was
clear. foreigness equals danger. And
then to seal the deal on this mass
hysteria of immigrant radicalism,
Congress passed the Immigration Act of
1921 and 1924, which led to significant
reductions in immigration to the United
States. Okay. Now, the last major
homeront development you need to know
about is significant migrations during
the war. And first, let me tell you
about migration in general during this
period. So, the conversion of many of
Americ's industries to wartime
production led to a massive rural to
urban migration. And with wartime
production being coordinated with
progressive efficiency by the federal
government, urban factory work became
much more accessible and attractive to
rural Americans needing work. And by
migrating into cities, they further
contributed to America's ongoing trend
of urbanization. For example, industrial
work in Chicago became a significant
draw for many American migrants owing to
its rapidly expanding steel and
meatacking and railroad industries. And
then New York City also attracted scores
of migrants due to growing demand for
its specialties in ship building and
garment manufacturing and financial
services. And so to tie it up with a
nice little bow, these migrations were
intimately connected to wartime federal
policy. The War Industries Board and the
National Labor Board coordinated
industrial production and also
stabilized wages. And such developments
proved very attractive to Americans
since labor shortages and wild price
fluctuations were destabilizing rural
economies and making it hard for farmers
to earn a consistent living.
Additionally, World War I cut off a lot
of international immigration, which
created even more of a demand for labor.
But now, let me tell you about a very
specific and massive migration during
this period, namely the Great Migration.
Now, I mentioned this in unit 6 because
it began in the 1890s, but during World
War I, it accelerated like crazy. So, in
case you forgot, the Great Migration
describes the movement of millions of
black Americans from the South into
northern and western cities. And they
made this trek for three distinct
reasons. First, black people moved to
escape segregation. Now, you'll recall
that Jim Crow laws had entirely
segregated southern states and led to
the marginalization and oppression of
black Americans. And the Supreme Court
got in on this marginalization party as
well. Py v. Ferguson upheld the racial
segregation of public facilities as long
as those separate facilities were equal
in quality. However, the black
facilities were never equal to the white
facilities. But even more, the very fact
of racial segregation humiliated black
Americans since it was very clear that
they were secondass citizens and so they
moved. Second, black people moved to
escape racial violence. So don't forget
that Jim Crow laws enabled racist
organizations like the Ku Klux Clan to
unleash an ongoing campaign of terror
against black southerners, including
thousands of public lynchings. And for
the most part, southern states never
really intervened legally to stop such
deadly violence. And then third, black
people migrated because they had limited
economic opportunities in the south. For
the most part, southern blacks worked as
sharecroppers on white-owned farms. And
the system essentially amounted to
slavery by a different name. And because
the sharecropping system drove black
farmers into debt by design, there was
little hope that they could become
economically self-sufficient. And so
they had to get out. And I wish I could
tell you that once these black Americans
left the South, they lived happily ever
after in the northern and western
racebelind utopias. But new. You see,
even after leaving the South and
settling in places where Jim Crow was
not the law of the land, black migrants
still experienced plenty of racial
discrimination. And one of the most
significant reasons black migrants
experienced racial hostility was because
white workers in these crowded
industrial cities saw black workers as
competition for their jobs. And such
resentment sometimes led to
extraordinary violence, as it did in the
Tulsa massacre in 1921. And the short
version goes like this. So many southern
blacks migrated to Tulsa, Oklahoma. And
for a variety of reasons, many of them
had become so successful that the
majority black Greenwood district had
come to be known as Black Wall Street.
And to put it mildly, Tulsa's white
population, many of whom still struggled
to make ends meet, began nursing a
serious resentment against these
prosperous blacks. And that resentment
boiled over in May of 1921 when an
unproven story about a black teen
assaulting a white woman began to spread
throughout the community. And in the
following days, white mobs looted and
burned the Greenwood district. and black
mobs retaliated with violence. And in
the end, nearly 40 people were dead and
it went down as one of the most severe
race riots in history. So, all in all,
yes, it was rough for those Americans
fighting Europeans over in the trenches,
but it wasn't much of a picnic for those
Americans who stayed home either. Well,
okay, you can click here to watch my
other videos for unit 7, or you can
click here to grab my video note, guys,
which are going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly crammed
into your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around, and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm lur.